Mbithe Nzomo

mbithe.nzomo@gmail.com · mbithenzomo.github.io · linkedin.com/in/mbithenzomo/

Research summary: My PhD explores the integration of data-driven and knowledge-driven AI in an architecture for personal health and wellness monitoring using wearable sensors. I look at two use cases: atrial fibrillation and stress.

Research interests: machine learning, ontologies, hybrid AI, sensor data, health monitoring.

Skills (languages/libraries/frameworks): Python, scikit-learn, Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, PyTorch, Protégé, OWL, SWRL, SPARQL.

EDUCATION

University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa

2021 - Present

PhD, Computer Science

Supervisor: Deshen Moodley. Working Title: "A Hybrid AI Framework for Data Fusion, Situation Analysis, and Decision Support Towards Precision Health"

University of Manchester, Manchester, United Kingdom

2018 - 2019

MSc, Advanced Computer Science (Distinction)

Supervisor: Angelo Cangelosi. Title: "Hello, Goodbye: Training Social Robots to Manage Interactions with Humans"

Strathmore University, Nairobi, Kenya

2012 - 2016

BSc, Informatics (2:1)

WORK EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant (part-time)

2023 - Present

<u>Adaptive and Cognitive Systems Lab at the Centre for Artificial Intellig</u>ence Research (CAIR)

Cape Town, South Africa

- Building a generalisable platform and workflow for deep learning projects within the lab.
- Consolidating and documenting codebases, datasets, and other research outputs.
- Developing a set of tutorials for technologies, libraries, and frameworks used in the lab.

Teaching Assistant, Data Science & AI (part-time)

2021 - 2022

Remote

iXperience

- Contributed to curriculum development, assisted in delivering lectures, and held office hours.
- Managed student internship projects with South Africa-based companies.

Senior Technology Consultant

2019 - 2021

<u>EY</u>

Nairobi, Kenya

- Executed end-to-end client engagements, including research, analysis, proposal development and implementation of emerging technologies in different organisations across a variety of sectors.
- Led data analytics team in client engagement involving financial data from the 2018/2019 financial year collected from 220 government facilities across 25 counties in Kenya.

Software Engineer

2016 - 2018

<u>Andela</u>

Nairobi, Kenya

- Built web apps and RESTful APIs. Primarily focused on back-end development using Python, including Flask and Django.
- Guided and mentored more than 50 developers by serving as a Technical Team Lead for simulated projects, as well as a Learning Facilitator for programming bootcamps.
- Engaged in remote and culturally diverse teams with team members distributed across Africa and the US.
- Invited to speak at multiple technology conferences, including the 2017 Propelify Innovation Festival in Hoboken, NJ, and the 2017 ASU+GSV Summit in Salt Lake City, UT.

FELLOWSHIPS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

2023
2022
2021
2021
2019
2018

PUBLICATIONS AND PREPRINTS

Nzomo, M.; Moodley, D. 2023. Semantic Technologies in Sensor-Based Personal Health Monitoring Systems: A Systematic Mapping Study. Under review at the Semantic Web Journal. Preprint available: doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2306.04335

Wanyana, T.; Nzomo, M.; Price, C. and Moodley, D. 2023. A Personal Health Agent for Decision Support in Arrhythmia Diagnosis. In Information and Communication Technologies for Ageing Well and e-Health. ICT4AWE ICT4AWE 2021 2022. Communications in Computer and Information Science, vol 1856. doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-37496-8_20

Wanyana, T.; Nzomo, M.; Price, C. and Moodley, D. 2022. Combining Machine Learning and Bayesian Networks for ECG Interpretation and Explanation. In Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies for Ageing Well and e-Health (ICT4AWE 2022), pages 81-92. doi.org/10.5220/0011046100003188

SELECTED CONFERENCES, WORKSHOPS, AND EVENTS

AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI 2024) Feb 2024 Extended abstract accepted for presentation at the Doctoral Consortium Vancouver, Canada International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2023) Aug 2023 Poster presentation, Africa Spotlight Poster Session Macau, S.A.R. Code for Science and Society (CS&S) Co-Design Workshop May 2023 Participant, Climate-Sensitive Infectious Disease Open Source Software Community of Practice Cape Town, South Africa Hasso Plattner Institute (HPI) Research Symposium 2023 Apr 2023 Poster and oral presentation Potsdam, Germany Southern African Conference for Artificial Intelligence Research (SACAIR 2022) Dec 2022 Unconference presentation Stellenbosch, South Africa Deep Learning Indaba 2022 Aug 2022 Poster presentation; selected in a competitive application process Tunis, Tunisia International Conference on ICT for Ageing Well and e-Health (ICT4AWE 2022) Feb 2022 Paper presentation Virtual Oxford Machine Learning Summer School (OxML 2021) Aug 2021 Participant; selected in a competitive application process Virtual

SERVICE, VOLUNTEERING, AND OUTREACH

Event Fund Selection Committee member - Code for Science and Society	Oct 2023 - Present
Short paper reviewer - Deep Learning Indaba	Aug - Sep 2023
Data Science track mentor - KamiLimu	Oct 2022 - May 2023
Professional mentor; scholarship application mentor - KamiLimu	Mar 2020 - May 2023
Application reviewer - Deep Learning Indaba	Mar - Apr 2023
Responsible Computer Science Challenge Judge - Mozilla Foundation	Jan - Mar 2023
Paper reviewer (Shadow PC) - ACM Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS)	Apr - Jun 2021
Technical writer (programming tutorials) - RealPython.org	May - Sep 2018
Technical writer (programming tutorials) - Scotch.io (since acquired by Digital Ocean)	Oct 2016 - Jan 2017
Co-organiser and coach - Django Girls (Nairobi, Mombasa, and Manchester)	May 2016 - Feb 2019

ACADEMIC TEACHING AND SUPERVISION

Teaching Assistant 2022 - Present

Department of Computer Science, University of Cape Town

Cape Town, South Africa

I am/have been a Teaching Assistant for the following first-year Python programming courses: CSC1015F, CSC1017F, CSC1019F, CSC1010H, and CSC1011H.

Honours Project Co-Supervisor

Grace Hopper Celebration (GHC) 2019

Participant; awarded the competitive GHC student scholarship to attend

2022

Oct 2019

Orlando, Florida

Department of Computer Science, University of Cape Town

Cape Town, South Africa

I co-supervised a team of honours (fourth-year) students as part of the year-long CSC4002W (Computer Science Honours Project) course. The project was titled "Deep Learning Algorithms in the Detection of Cardiovascular Diseases Using Electrocardiogram Data".

Last updated: 23 October 2023